Software Engineering Radio episode 19
concurrency part two.
Welcome to a new episode on Software
Engineering Radio. This is part two of
our concurrency topic. This time we talk
about synchronization and concurrency
patterns.
In the first part of our concurrency
episodes, we defined the terms a bit and
talked about challenges like dead lock
you have to deal with when you do
concurrent programming. In this episode,
we will go a little bit further and
discuss how to do synchronization and
what concurrency patterns are there.
General remark on our concurrency
episodes might be useful here.
Please do not consider our concurrency
episodes as a general encouragement to
use concurrency for everything and
everywhere. We would actually recommend
to to think a lot about when to use
concurrency and how because there is
always an overhead associated with
concurrency program with threads with
multiple processes. So in the most
common still most common case of a
single CPU hardware, you might not gain
a lot from it. You you get maybe a a
better reacting application, but you
also lose some performance. So take care
where to use concurrency and how to use
it.
Think about servers. There there you
have to use it, but always beware of the
overhead associated with concurrency. So
there are also some patterns or
techniques out there to avoid
concurrency and get applications that
react as if they were concurrent and one
of this is reactive design.
Yeah, so in many cases, especially when
only one CPU is involved, a reactive
design
using the reactor pattern can achieve
quite high performance, as high as a
concurrent design. The reactor pattern
is used to dispatch events from multiple
sources using a single thread.
As long as the computation is short
lasting, this is a good design. So, but
in case the computation after the
arrival of a event lasts longer, you
cannot you cannot circumvent that with a
single thread and still be reactive. So,
you need multiple threads and here you
have basically two options, at least two
options.
First, use a concurrent design with one
thread per event source, but that has
its limitation. For example, imagine one
source is quite busy, where in the other
um
source doesn't emit events so regularly.
In this case, you would only use one
thread and the other thread would mostly
run idle.
So, basically the the threads are not
shared across the event sources. A more
advanced solution to that is using
reactor in conjunction with a leader
followers pattern
to achieve a high scalability
and best resource usage. But that is
something we will discuss in part three.
So, let's get back to synchronization
and concurrency.
The The first form we will discuss is
the very simplest is a simple lock
and it's basically what we told last
episode.
It's about two or more threads sharing
some common data, for example, variable
or some resource like database
connection.
The access to this
shared
resources needs to be protected. So in
this case you simply use some kind of
lock and
therefore control which of the multiple
threads gets the resource. A more
complex form of it is the monitor
object.
A monitor object is basically an object
where every single method is
protected by some lock. So you have to
program in every method
or at the beginning of every method you
have to check if you have the lock. The
the object, the monitor object, has the
lock and after the method is completed
you have to release the lock. So the the
granularity is very coarse. You you have
always the whole object locked. So
monitor objects are quite heavyweight
and of course it's very or it is at
least dangerous to to use monitor
objects because if you forget to get
some lock or to release a lock you have
the problem that um
your monitor object doesn't work
anymore. Especially cumbersome and
error-prone is of course the the case of
an error. You have to check that you
also release the lock otherwise the
money will be locked forever.
Another problem is you have to take care
if you call an other method from within
your method.
This can at least lead to deadlocks.
If your locks are not re-entrant and
re-entrant means if you as a lock holder
have already the lock
you You also get the lock again and
don't have to wait until the lock is
released. Nevertheless, the advantage of
monitor object is actually that it's
very simple, very easy to use, very
clean,
and therefore it's the default or it's
it's a built-in feature of the Java
language. It's the way how
synchronization is implemented in Java.
And
therefore some of the problems don't
occur there, of course, because you
don't have to care to get the lock or
release the lock. Another thing I I want
to mention about monitor object, of
course, you can use monitor objects as a
mutex replacement if you simply define
an object that synchronizes, that gets
the lock, you can use it to to
yeah, implement simple mutexes with
monitor objects.
Yeah, the next pattern we want to
discuss is scope locking. Scope locking
has been documented in POSIX.2.
And scope locking helps you to actually
release a lock again because in many
cases
it is quite easy that a lock is not
released, either by a programmatic error
and that just the programmer forgot to
put in a release statement in that case
of the if branch or the like or an
exception occurred and just a totally
different
execution branch is chosen.
So, scope locking encapsulates the
acquire in the constructor
and the release in the destructor.
This way, as soon as you instantiate
the guard who implements that,
the lock is acquired and as soon as the
the scope is left uh
by by any means, either because you just
uh
from that method or because an exception
occurred, the destructor will ensure
that the lock is released.
Of course, uh this only works uh in
programming languages uh that have a
destructor like C++. Uh in Java, um we
have no destructor and therefore, well,
at least not um
the in in the classic sense. So, in
Java, this pattern uh just cannot be
used. And another pattern from POSA 2 um
is active object. Monitor objects that
we just introduced before are okay, but
they are passive and they do not own any
threads, so they must be driven
explicitly by other threads.
Encapsulating threads in so-called
active objects that follow the active
object pattern is a good idea for for
typical worker threads that accept
input, perform an asynchronous
computation, and then forward the
results to any other object, potentially
another active object. Active objects uh
have typically an input queue, which is
of course protected by a lock because it
gets accessed by the client or the
invoking thread who uh hands over and
computation request, and it is accessed,
of course, by the thread of the active
object. This way, um the active object
can accept multiple orders, multiple
input data while computing uh results
based on the previous uh input. The the
active object is reactive to the outside
while it's is still busy computing based
on the orders uh previously inserted.
Different strategies exist on how to
handle the cases when the queue is full.
Invoking client threads uh might block
when the queue is full and just have to
wait until it's empty again. The thread
of the active object itself will
typically block on the queue as long as
it is empty. One brief discussion about
queues. Queues often require dynamic
memory allocations and synchronization.
So, this in turn can cause really
measurable jitter and then in real-time
systems, this is the reason to minimize
the number of queues used especially in
the critical path. And here again,
architects should consider how to avoid
queues for example by using an reactive
design.
One problem if you have these active
objects, the clients have to deal with
the queue, so they have to put in the
request in the queue, so that's not so
problematic, but they also have to get
the results from the computation back
and that's a bit
Yeah,
it's not very easy to do if you have to
consider all this asynchronicity in your
client code. So, there is another
pattern. It's called future.
And a future is basically that your
active object, for example, gives you a
placeholder for the result and fills the
placeholder for the result later on. You
as a client of the active object don't
have to deal with queues, you don't have
to check
you just can use your future object as a
normal result object from from the
active object and get the result out of
the future object whenever you need. Of
course, it could be that the result
isn't computed yet because the active
object wasn't fast enough or the client
was faster at the this point. So, you
usually implement
a future object with blocking get
methods. If you want to take out the
result of the future object, the get
methods or whatever
they are called,
block until the the thing is computed,
the output is
result is computed.
And usually future objects also have
non-blocking check methods
if you don't want to force your client
to block for the result or until the
result is computed by the active object.
So, such a design
is only practical, of course, if only
one result will be computed by the
active object or by the asynchronous
object because if you have more than one
result, you can't simply
or you can't simplify the access for the
client in that way as described in
future object.
Double check locking is another pattern
that we want to discuss in the context
of concurrent designs.
Double check locking is useful every
time you do something lazily, every time
you do something on demand. For example,
in the case of lazy instantiation, one
of the examples of lazy instantiation is
the case of a singleton. Alex, could you
explain what a singleton is briefly?
The purpose of the singleton pattern is
to ensure that there is just one
instance of an object.
So, how do you do this? You usually
write a method called instance and in
this method, you check if the object is
already created. If it is, you just
return the reference or the point to the
object. Otherwise, you create it and
store the reference for later use.
The singleton pattern is actually a
pattern where are some controversies
about it because it is not so different
from using global variables because
usually you use it for a global
resource, a resource that is only
instantiated once in your whole program.
And that's a problem, of course, because
you you usually have reference and
dependencies spread all over your code
to this global instance. So, use the
singleton pattern only
when appropriate and try to avoid it as
far as possible.
So, singletons
basically erode your architecture. I
know that Kevlin Henney, who I really
value
as an expert on object orientation, he
can write episodes, he can write long
articles on why singletons are such a
bad idea. Still, they're an excellent
use case for double-check locking. So,
yeah,
discussing about singletons, we should
ask whether lazy instantiation and and
doing things lazily on demand in a
concurrent design is generally a good
practice or not. So, so I have no final
answer to that, but generally I think
it's a good idea to avoid on-demand
actions even if lazy acquisition in
general um saves you resources because
you would acquire them only when you
when actually needed. So, I'm kind of
bit torn what to recommend on this
topic. But, continuing with double-check
locking, the problem is as follows. So,
in case of lazy instantiation, for
example, you would need to check whether
the the resource the object, the
singleton to be instantiated uh is
already available. So, if you do that
not synchronized, um then you can easily
have the the chance that just another
thread did the same thing and
instantiated
the singleton or the common resource,
and you have suddenly two singletons,
two
resources, and it would actually
override the same variable, the the
reference to the singleton. So, doing
that in a synchronized way, you would
just put a synchronized statement in
Java across that critical section when
you check for the existence of that
resource and when you done
instantiate the resource.
But that really slows down your
execution because this check is always
in the critical path. Every time you
access the resource, you will use the
so-called instance method, for example,
of that
of a singleton, you will be required to
acquire and release the lock, which is
quite slow. So, the initial check for
for the existence
of that resource singleton should be
outside of any synchronized or locking
statement. And here comes the
double-check locking pattern. Um the
solution is to do an initial check for
the existence of the resource without
synchronization
and only in the case when it's not
existing yet, acquire the lock and check
again whether it's already existing.
Because while you waited on the lock,
while you try to acquire the lock,
somebody else might have created it
already. So, double-check locking helps
you to avoid the overall expensive
locking mechanism and you will be
required to acquire the lock only in the
case when it's not existing yet.
And other warning here, please don't use
double-check locking in Java because it
will not work. We will put a link on our
website for an exact explanation why it
is, but
there is fundamental flaw
Well, it's not a flaw, it's the way
bytecode and virtual machine is actually
designed in Java. There is no way to
implement double-check locking pattern
in Java without
breaking in some very special
situations. So, don't use it.
You have no chance to implement it.
There have been a lot of threats in the
internet on it. So, check it out. It's
dangerous.
Yeah, so with this we conclude our first
introduction of some patterns in the
concurrency domain. We will continue in
part three with more advanced patterns.
So, in this episode we want to continue
with some architectural considerations.
The number of threads seems to be
a critical topic and and reason for some
flame wars. For example, when I talk to
the embedded people doing
embedded projects,
developing embedded applications for the
automotive or automation domain, they
tell me that historically it has always
proved that they use as many threads as
necessary for every small responsibility
they would introduce a separate thread.
They would have queues between those
threads. So, the the overall design
looked like a a mailboxes system
where the the workers put orders for
other responsibilities into their input
queues. And at the end they they ended
up with dozens or even hundreds of
threads. And the argument for that
design, which they tell me, is that they
could at the end fine-tune the system
with priorities, assigning individual
priorities to the threads, and and get
the optimal best result. I don't believe
in in this design, to be honest. I think
reducing the number of threads to a
reasonable number, which in my opinion
is somewhere below a dozen,
is a good practice. Every time I was
involved in such an embedded project and
we designed the application with the a
reasonable low number of thread, we were
still able to achieve the the necessary
real-time properties and the scalability
and the performance, especially of the
system. And the design often quite was
easier and it was easier also to track
and and debug the system as I didn't
have to check dozens of queue content.
So, Alex, what is your experience for
the enterprise domain?
As you said, it's a very difficult topic
and actually I would recommend to move
the decision how many threads to have to
to run time. I would always recommend to
make thread pools configurable and to
actually, yeah, well, make this
threading strategy configurable because
it's nearly impossible to estimate or
plan in advance how your application
will run on the
the real production hardware and usually
the production hardware also changes
over the lifetime of an application.
People put in more CPUs or more memory
and therefore the whole thing, yeah,
behaves very different. So, it's a good
idea to not to design or to make a very
fixed design front up and
make these things like number of threads
not configurable.
You just used the term thread pool. I
guess that is something an advanced
topic that we will discuss in part
three, but briefly introduce what what
you mean by thread pool.
Okay. Threads are very expensive, not as
expensive as processors as we discussed
in the first episode, but still are very
expensive to create. So, a design
pattern there is to have a pool of
threads and
um if you need a new thread, don't
create a new one, just use one out of
the pool and um and delegate the re-
responsibility to do the job to one of
the
empty running or not used threads from
the thread pool.
Okay. And afterwards, you would have to
release the thread
again to the thread pool so that you
could reuse it the next time.
Exactly.
So, yeah, my my personal opinion on how
many threads are are necessary in a
system, for every part of the system
that is highly interactive and needs
therefore to be highly reactive, I
recommend to use a separate thread. This
is for example the case in in the user
interface design. Secondly,
good argumentation or good reasoning is
every time the control logic often
separated control flow of a concurrent
design is easier to understand and
maintain than a
highly reactive design using the
reactor. I would prefer the the control
logic being separated in a in a separate
thread.
And the third argument is use a reactive
design with a thread pool in case you
have long-lasting jobs. We will discuss
this kind of design in the third part.
Yep. Okay.
Um some of the recommendations I did for
configuration of thread pools also um
are true for the priority stuff. And I
guess it's the only way to to assign
priority to threads is to measure later
on and and then uh set the priorities
for the single threads in your system.
So, it's a lot about measuring in my
opinion.
Yeah, the signing priorities is a quite
difficult topic. Most cases I've seen
that it's only done
with some first estimations.
Here Doug Lea gives some
recommendations, for example, having for
crisis management and interaction the
highest priorities.
Then for IO and background tasks the
mid-level
priorities and the lowest priorities for
the jobs
that should run when nothing else is
really necessary to be performed. But
finally at the end, the fine-tuning is
almost always done by trial and error
basically. You try how your system
performs, you do long-running tests,
overnight tests, and then check the
results and check the performance
on whether you could achieve a better
performance and better real-time
properties by changing any of the
priorities.
A difficult and and challenging topic is
priority inversions, but that again we
save for later episode.
Mhm.
If we are we talk about the number of
threads, we should talk also a bit about
resources. Um if you develop in
multi-threaded environments, you always
have to take a look at where your
resources are from and how scarce they
are. I mean,
um if you have locks and they are
operating system locks, there might be a
number of locks your operating system
can handle without a problem, and then
there might be a a number your operating
system can't deal anymore. So so same
for number of threads, um always take
into account these resources might be
very expensive
and that they are
not an
infinite number of locks out there if
you have an environment with these
constraints. So, take a number take the
number of threads as a very important
number in your consideration. It it
might trash your application completely
if you have too many of them
and or too fine-grained threads for too
too little
things to do.
Yeah, so that the general recommendation
is to to handle
concurrency
as an architectural topic because it has
a very strong influence on on the
architecture and at the end at the
non-functional properties of your
system. To sum up our second episode on
concurrency, we would like to give the
the recommendation for general
concurrent and network programming to
read Posix 2. We put the link on our
homepage as usual and especially for
Java developers but also for non-Java
developers a good book on the topic is
concurrent programming in Java by Doug
Lea. This is one of my favorite books
about concurrency. It describes
step-by-step with many examples on how
to do good design with Java and
generally do good design in
object-oriented applications. Alex,
final word to say?
So, thanks for listening. As always, we
would be happy to get feedback from you
to complete our concurrency series. The
next episode will most probably deal
with building highly scalable servers
and advanced patterns in the concurrency
domain. Thanks for listening. Bye-bye.
This was another episode of Software
Engineering Radio.
The Software Engineering Radio team
wants to thank Henning Pauly for
providing the music as well as
lipsyn.com for hosting and bandwidth.
For more information on the podcast,
past episodes, and feedback, go to
se-radio.net.